Guide to the Sisterhood is Global Institute Records, 1963-2010 and undated, bulk 1980-2002 RL.01185
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sisterhood is Global Institute records
1963-2010 and undated, bulk 1980-2002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sisterhood is Global Institute
RL.01185
121.5 Linear Feet
In response to Robin Morgan's book, Sisterhood is Global, the Sisterhood is Global Institute was founded in 1984 with Karen Berry as its first director. Its purpose was to mobilize international support on women’s rights issues and educate various communities around the world on women's rights and human rights issues. The records of the Sisterhood is Global Institute (SIGI) span the years from 1965 to 2005, with the bulk of the material ranging from 1980 to 2002. Materials such as correspondence, administrative files, publications drafts, manuals, newsletters, flyers, photographs, videos, and sound recordings provide a record of the work and the organizational structure of SIGI from its inception to its present activities at the beginning of the 21st century. The documents in the collection illustrate SIGI's efforts to discuss, debate, and act on a variety of women's issues around the world, including voting rights and political representation; reproductive rights; violence against women; education for women; and the socio-economic status of women.
72,532 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In addition, original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Some use copies are available in the collection. Otherwise, Technical Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Sisterhood is Global Institute Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2001, 2003, 2004, 2009, and 2015 as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Historical Note
Missing Title
1984 Sisterhood Is Global Network (SIGN) and SIGI’s Urgent Action Alert System established for mobilizing international support on women’s rights issues Sisterhood is Global Institute (SIGI) founded, with Karen Berry as Executive Director. Sisterhood is Global strategy meeting convened in New York as a follow-up to the publication of Robin Morgan's anthology Sisterhood Is Global
1985 UN Third World Conference on Women held in Nairobi
1988 SIGI’s headquarters moved to New Zealand. Appointment of Executive Director Marilyn Waring
1993 SIGI’s headquarters moved to Maryland, USA. Mahnaz Afkhami appointed Executive Director
1994 SIGN Dialogues conferences held in Athens, Washington D.C., and Zambia
1995 UN Fourth World Conference on Women held in Beijing
1996 Claiming Our Rights: A Manual for Women's Human Rights Education in Muslim Societies published as part of SIGI’s project on Women’s Human Rights Education (HRE). The HRE Project launched the same year as a series of workshops on the rights of women in Muslim societies SIGI’s conference Beijing and Beyond: Implementing the Platform for Action in Muslim Societies convened in May
1997 SIGI’s conference Rights of Passage: An International Conference on Women's Human Rights Education held in Washington D.C.
1998 SIGI’s conference Eliminating Violence against Women in Muslim Societies to be held in Jordan is cancelled, and instead an Expert Group Meeting on Eliminating Violence against Women and Girls is convened in Washington, D.C. First version of SIGI’s training manual Safe and Secure: Eliminating Violence against Women and Girls in Muslim Societies published
1999 SIGI’s office moved to Montreal, Canada; Greta Hofmann Nemiroff appointed President
2001 New projects launched, among which initiatives related to leadership building, fisheries’ depletion, and development of micro-credit programs for single mothers
2004 SIGI’s office to be permanently located in New York
Collection Overview
The records of the Sisterhood is Global Institute (SIGI) span the years from 1965 to 2005, with the bulk of the material documenting the Institute's activities and administration from 1980 to 2002. Through correspondence, administrative files, subject files, drafts of publications, newsletter, manuals, reports, photographs, videos, and sound recordings, the collection provides an in-depth record of the work and the organizational structure of SIGI from its inception in 1984 to its present activities at the beginning of the 21st century, and documents its efforts to discuss, debate, and act on a variety of women's issues around the world, including voting rights and political representation; reproductive rights; violence against women; education for women; and the socio-economic status of women. Subject files created by SIGI researchers provide additional materials on prostitution, rape, the status of women in developing countries and rural areas, the legal status of women, and the concept of human rights. In the 1990s particular emphasis was paid to women's issues in Muslim societies. Much of the Institute's role is an educational one, as evidenced by the many folders of manuals, newsletters, news alerts, workshops, and conferences on women's issues, including materials on two U.N. World Conferences on Women. The collection offers many documents relating to SIGI publications, including the book Sisterhood is Global; and editions in various languages of In Our Own Words, Safe and Secure, and Claiming Our Rights. In addition to documenting SIGI's activism on behalf of women, the collection also provides a record of the Institute's organizational structure and functioning; although there is very little from the earliest years, there are many records for the 1990s, particularly for the years 1999-2002, during Greta Hofmann Nemiroff's tenure as President. Other individuals whose active roles in the development of Sisterhood is Global Institute are documented through correspondence and writings include Marilyn Waring, Robin Morgan, and Tatiana Mamonova. Many smaller files of correspondence and writings from individual members offer a profile of SIGI's international constituency drawn from over 70 countries.
One of the smallest folder groups, the Correspondence Series offers a sampling of routine requests and expressions of interest from individuals writing to the Sisterhood is Global Institute. Several folders house petitions and protest letters initiated by SIGI. There is also a group of exchanges related to the New Zealand "girlcott" organized in part by Marilyn Waring, president of SIGI at the time.
The largest series in the collection, the Administrative Files Series is divided into five subseries: Membership Files, Greta Hofmann Nemiroff, Financial Papers, Funding Files, and Other Records. The series offers an extensive profile of SIGI’s international constituency which in 2002 included members from over 70 countries worldwide. More extensive records are available for some eminent international figures such as Robin Morgan and Tatyana Mamonova, as well as for Marilyn Waring who acted as Executive Director of SIGI in New Zealand. The files of Greta Hofmann Nemiroff, the Financial Files, and the Other Records Subseries provide a record of the administrative management of SIGI’s resources, with the most detailed records dating from the period between 1996 and 2002. The funding history of SIGI, together with the documentation of grants and donors, is located in the Funding Files subseries, which also contains correspondence and financial reports on SIGI’s core projects like the Human Rights Education Program (HRE) and the Project on Eliminating the Violence Against Women (VAW).
The Project Files Series documents the stages and implementation of the HRE Program and the development of new projects, among which VAW, the Learning Partnership Projects, and the Building Local Leaders Initiative. The HRE Program, a reflection of the continuous work of SIGI on the issue of women’s human rights, is a series of 12 workshops whose aim is to promote the concept of women’s rights in Islamic cultures and provide women strategies and networking skills for the assertion of these rights. The series contains reports and correspondence with facilitators from nine countries where these workshops have been conducted, as well as materials on other countries considered for the extension of the project. Included in the series is also a record of SIGI Urgent Action Alerts, a system of immediate alerts and global calls for actions in response to discriminatory practices and cases of abuse in different regions of the world.
The Publications Series contains drafts, editions, and translations of workshop manuals, part of SIGI programs, as well as records related to anthologies edited by SIGI members, such as the volumes Muslim Women and the Politics of Participation and Strategizing for Safety. A large portion of the series is comprised of various translations of Claiming Our Rights, a manual containing definitions and learning exercises designed to illustrate the concept of women’s rights in different social contexts and to stimulate discussions on the status of women in Muslim societies. Other publications presented in the series include Safe and Secure, a manual designed for SIGI workshops on violence against women, and In Our Own Words, a companion guide with strategies for workshop facilitators. The series also contains all the issues of SIGI News, a biannual newsletter covering SIGI’s activities and providing a venue for announcements of different events.
The Conferences and Programs Series is divided into SIGI and Other Events subseries and contains records of the preparation and logistics for conferences organized by SIGI, as well as materials from major international meetings on subjects related to women’s rights. SIGI’s two conferences Religion, Culture, and Women’s Rights in the Muslim World (1994) and Beijing and Beyond (1996) were specifically organized in connection to the 4th World Conference on Women which took place in Beijing, which is also covered in the series. Other SIGI conferences extensively represented in the series include Rights of Passage (1997) and the Expert Group Meeting on Eliminating Violence against Girls and Women (1998) which evolved from the preparation for a conference with the same title, initially scheduled to take place in Jordan. Materials on the two World Conferences on Women, in Nairobi and Beijing, as well as other global events such as the UN conference on human rights in 1993 and the World March of Women in 2000, is found in the Other Events Subseries.
The Photographic Materials Series depicts moments from conferences attended or organized by SIGI, visits, and some of the workshops conducted by SIGI in different countries.
The Subject Files Series contains materials collected by SIGI on a wide range of subjects related to women, from reproductive rights and motherhood to the consequences of armed conflicts. A large section of papers and studies in the series, mostly dating from the late 1980s and early 1990s, is devoted to the socio-economic status of women and their situation in developing countries and rural areas. Another large group of materials, whose time range extends beyond the 1990s, reflects on SIGI’s development of new projects, and the materials focus increasingly on the legal status of women, the concept of women’s human rights, and the subject of violence against women which includes extensive collection of reports and article on domestic violence, prostitution, rape, and war crimes.
The Organizations Series contains information gathered by SIGI staff about numerous international and regional organizations and networks working in the sphere of women’s and human rights, development, and law. Highlighted organizations include the Association of Women in Development, the Canadian Council for Refugees, Equality Now, Feminist Majority, Isis International, the International Women's Health Coalition, the National Council for Research on Women, the Women's Environment and Development Organization, and the United Nations. There is some correspondence with former First Lady Hilary Clinton.
Like the Subject Files Series, the Geographic Files Series also functions as a vertical file created by SIGI staff for internal use, containing informative articles, clippings, reports, many newsletters, and other materials on women's issues in over 100 countries from Afghanistan to Zimbabwe. Countries with the most materials are Pakistan, Phillippines, and Malaysia.
The Audiovisual Materials Series contains over 20 videocassettes and audio recordings of SIGI events or programs originating in other countries. Topics and events include a forum on "feminist family values," conferences on women's issues, women's rights in Muslim societies, domestic violence, politics and power in the Phillippines and in other countries, and educational programming on money and job training. Use copies are available for most of these items; otherwise Technical Services staff will need to arrange to have use copies made. Please contact reference staff before coming to use this series.
Finally, the boxes in the Memorabilia Series house several large and small protest banners.
The collection includes some financial records, webpage content, and translations of published material in electronic form, found listed in the Electronic Formats Series under the appropriate series. The documents are maintained on the electronic records server. Consult a reference archivist for access to them.
Addition (2009-0070) (5850 items; 7.8 lin. ft.; dated 1985-2003) contains administrative records and correspondence, financial reports and documents, legal documents, membership information, annual reports, and publicity files. Also included are 20 cassette tapes recording the Sisterhood is Global Strategy Meeting (1984), founding the Institute, and 11 floppy discs that have been transferred to Duke's Electronic Records server. This addition has not been processed; materials have been reboxed but not incorporated into the remainder of the collection. Please see a reference archivist if you have questions.
Addition (2015-01480) (1500 items; 3 lin. ft.; dated 1982-2010) contains administrative records and correspondence.
Audiocassettes; Photographs; Women -- Congresses; Women in politics; Non-governmental organizations; Videocassettes; International organizations; International agencies; Rape; Prostitution; Electronic records; Women in development -- International cooperation; Women -- Social conditions; Women's rights -- International cooperation; Human Rights; Women's rights; Morgan, Robin, 1941-; Mamonova, Tatiana; Nemiroff, Greta Hofmann; Sisterhood is Global Institute; Sisterhood is Global Institute; Waring, Marilyn
- Correspondence Series, 1984-2003, 3 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists primarily of routine correspondence with individuals and organizations who have expressed interest in Sisterhood is Global Institute (SIGI) and its publications. The general correspondence and the signed-on letters folders contain numerous petitions and protest letters. The highlight of the series is the extended material on the New Zealand Girlcott Initiative launched by Marilyn Waring in 1985. Organized chronologically by year, then alphabetically by folder name.
  - 1984-1992 (Box CORR1)
    - General correspondence (Box CORR1)
  - 1985
    - Girlcott Initiative, New Zealand, Feb.-Oct., 4 folders (Box CORR1)
    - Letter to Robin Morgan of Ms. Magazine, Oct. 17 (Box CORR1)
    - Lorna Gordon and Associates, Caribbean, Jamaica, July (Box CORR1)
  - 1988
    - University of Waikato, New Zealand, Oct. (Box CORR1)
  - 1989-1991
    - Mailing lists, SIGI network (Box CORR1)
  - 1989-1992
    - Financial correspondence (Box CORR1)
  - 1990-1992
    - Form letters (Box CORR1)
  - 1991
    - New Zealand Government Labour Department, student job search (Box CORR1)
  - 1992
    - Portugal, Ana Maria Peru, Aug. (Box CORR1)
  - 1993
    - Inquiries, Bethesda office (Box CORR1)
    - Ivekovic, Rada, Croatia/Yugoslavia, June-Sept. (Box CORR1)
    - Oussedik, Fatma, Algeria (Box CORR1)
  - 1994 (Box CORR2)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box CORR2)
  - 1994-1996
    - Konie, Gwendoline (Box CORR2)
  - 1995
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 2 folders (Box CORR2)
  - 1996
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 2 folders (Box CORR2)
  - 1996-1997
    - Signed-on letters (Box CORR2)
  - 1998
    - General correspondence (Box CORR2)
    - Signed-on letters (Box CORR2)
  - 1999
    - General correspondence (Box CORR2)
    - Signed-on letters
      - General (Box CORR2)
      - Amnesty (Box CORR2)
  - 1999-2001
    - Shukla, Sonal, India (Box CORR2)
  - 2000
    - Communications with field coordinators (Box CORR2)
    - Dean, Mary E., West Virginia, May-June (Box CORR2)
    - Giri, Manjula (Box CORR2)
  - 2000 (Box CORR3)
    - Holiday greetings, sent and received, Dec. (Box CORR3)
    - Letter from Greta Hofmann Nemiroff to field coordinators, Dec. (Box CORR3)
    - O'Neill, Lidia Falcón, Spain (Box CORR3)
    - Pietilä, Hilkka, Women's International Network on Gender and Human Security (Box CORR3)
    - Vaziri, Haleh, Canada (Box CORR3)
  - 2000-2001
    - Sob, Durga (Box CORR3)
    - Zill, Anne B., Center for Ethics in Action, Me. (Box CORR3)
  - 2000-2002
    - Rivero, Isel (Box CORR3)
  - 2000-2003
    - Herman, Louis (Box CORR3)
    - Morgan, Robin (Box CORR3)
  - 2001
    - Foley, Ellen, Michigan State University, The Internet and Women's Democratic Networking, Mar. (Box CORR3)
    - Hachtroudi, Fariba, Canada, Feb. (Box CORR3)
    - General (Box CORR3)
    - Sadria, Mahbobeh, Feb. 23 (Box CORR3)
    - Tokhtakhodjaeva, Marfua, May (Box CORR3)
  - 2001-2002
    - Abdo, Nahla (Box CORR3)
    - General (Box CORR3)
  - 2002
    - Afghanistan Reconstruction Support Committee, June (Box CORR3)
    - Letter from Gul Joya Jafri, Afghan Women's Organization, Sept. (Box CORR3)
    - Letter to Annan, Kofi, other correspondence, June-July (Box CORR3)
    - Letters from Yvonne Deutsch, Mar.-Apr. (Box CORR3)
    - Nemiroff, Greta
      - To Jean Chrétien, July 16 (Box CORR3)
      - To Renato Martino, May 7 (Box CORR3)
    - Oumnia, April 29 (Box CORR3)
  - 2003
    - Letters of protest, petitions signed by SIGI, Jan.-Feb. (Box CORR3)
    - Saadawi, Nawal El to Greta Nemiroff, April 19 (Box CORR3)
- Administrative Files Series, 1975-2004 and undated, 49 boxes
  The Administrative Files Series is divided into five subseries: Membership Files Subseries, Greta Hofmann Nemiroff Subseries, Financial Papers Subseries, Financial Papers Subseries, and Other Records Subseries which are described below. The series contains a wide range of organizational records, predominantly personnel files and correspondence with members, financial records, annual reports and meeting minutes, and documentation on grants, projects, and donors. The materials represent best the period when SIGI was based in Maryland and Canada, the 1990s and onward, while records from SIGI's inception in New York and the years in New Zealand are sparse.
  - Membership Files Subseries, 1975-2001 and undated, 7 boxes
    Contains correspondence, biographies of current and former members, membership forms, and published work and articles about members or their work. Includes more extensive material on international feminists and prominent SIGI members such as Tatyana Mamonova, Robin Morgan, and Marilyn Waring. The series provides a close view of SIGI’s inner structure, constituency, and growth through the 1990s. Organized alphabetically by category, then by last name.
    - Current Members (Box M1)
      - Afkhami, Mahnaz, Iran, 1986-2000 and undated (Box M1)
      - Agosin, Marjorie, Chile, 1980s-2001, 2 folders (Box M1)
      - Aidoo, Ama Ata, Ghana, 1990-1999 (Box M1)
      - Allaghi, Farida, Libya, 1981-1999 (Box M1)
      - Almana, Aisha, Saudi Arabia, 1989-2001 (Box M1)
      - Aloni, Shulamit, Israel, 1985-1999 (Box M1)
      - Anwar, Zainah, 1998-1999 (Box M1)
      - Arsanios, Afifa, Lebanon, 1994-2001 and undated (Box M1)
      - Arungu-Olende, Rose Adhiambo, Kenya, 1997-1999 and undated (Box M1)
      - As, Berit, Norway, 1982-1999 and undated (Box M1)
      - Awekotuku, Ngahuia Te, New Zealand, 1986-1999 (Box M1)
      - Berry, Karen, Emeritus Member, 1989-1999 (Box M1)
      - Calvera, Leonor, Argentina, 1987-1999 (Box M1)
      - Chabaku, Motlalepula, Southern Africa, 1987-1999 (Box M1)
      - Charlesworth, Hillary, 2000-2001 and undated (Box M1)
      - Chase, Nova, Namibia, 1990-1999 (Box M1)
      - Cheng, Lucie, China, 1984-1999 (Box M1)
    - Current Members (Box M2)
      - Corral, Thais, Brazil, 1997-1999 (Box M2)
      - Coseteng, Anna Domingue, Philippines, 1988-1999 (Box M2)
      - Cuales, Sonia, Caribbean, Trinidad, and Tobago, 1993-1997 (Box M2)
      - De Briceno, Mercedes Pulido, Venezuela, 1992-1999 (Box M2)
      - De Hedervary, Claire, Belgium, 1988-1999 (Box M2)
      - De Sheppard Macedo, Raquel, Uruguay, 1988-1999 (Box M2)
      - Delphy, Christine, France, 1986-1999 (Box M2)
      - De Troy, Collette, 2000-2001 and undated (Box M2)
      - Deutsch, Yvonne, 1995-2001 (Box M2)
      - Dowse, Sara, Australia, 1985-1999 (Box M2)
      - El Saadawi, Nawal, Egypt, 1985-2001 (Box M2)
      - Evatt, Elizabeth, 1990-2000 (Box M2)
      - Fakhro, Munira, Bahrain, 1994-1999 (Box M2)
      - Falcon, Lidia, Spain, 1982-1999 (Box M2)
      - Ghurayyib, Rose, Lebanon, 1990-1999 (Box M2)
      - Giles, Pat, Australia, 1985-2001 and undated (Box M2)
      - Giri, Manjula, Nepal, 1985-1999 (Box M3)
      - Goonatilake, Hema, Sri Lanka, 1990-1999 and undated (Box M3)
      - Griffen, Vanessa, Fiji, 1975-2000, 2 folders (Box M3)
      - Guifarro, Blanca, Hondruas, 1993-1999 and undated (Box M3)
      - Habib, Miriam, Pakistan, 1985-1999 and undated (Box M3)
      - Hierro, Graciela, Mexico, 1996-1999 and undated (Box M3)
      - Higuchi, Keiko, Japan, 1980-1999 and undated (Box M3)
      - Kamal, Zahira, Palestine, 1989-1999 (Box M3)
      - Khader Asma, Jordan, 1997-1999 and undated (Box M3)
      - Kolb, Ingrid, Germany, 1999 and undated (Box M3)
      - Konie, Gwendoline, Zambia, 1985-2001 (Box M3)
      - Korosi, Suzanne, Hungary, 1987-1999 and undated (Box M3)
      - Lee, Tai-Young, South Korea, 1985-1999 and undated (Box M3)
      - Leonard, Diane, Great Britain, 1992-1999 (Box M3)
      - Lugo, Carmen, Mexico, 1986-1999 (Box M3)
      - Mamonova, Tatyana, Russia, 1985-2001 and undated, 2 folders (Box M4)
      - McCAfferty, Nell, Ireland, 1987-1999 and undated (Box M4)
      - Mernissi, Fatima, Morocco, 1978-2001 and undated (Box M4)
      - Mongella, Gertrude, Tanzania, 1995-1998 (Box M4)
      - Morgan, Robin
        - Correspondence, 1990-2001, 3 folders (Box M4)
        - Documents sent by her, 1993 Sept. 1 (Box M4)
        - Alida Scheuer Foundation, 1997-1998 (Box M4)
      - Muchena, Olivia, Zimbabwe, 1985-1999 (Box M4)
      - Navanethem, Pillay, South Africa, 1997-1999 (Box M4)
      - Nemiroff, Greta, Hofmann, 1986-1999 (Box M4)
      - Ogundipe-Leslie, Molara, 1987-1999 and undated (Box M5)
      - Ogunleye, Chief Bisi, Nigeria, 1999 (Box M5)
      - Okwenje, Elizabeth, Uganda, 1997-1999 (Box M5)
      - Papandreou, Margarita, Greece, 1985-1999 (Box M5)
      - Pietilä, Hilkka, Finland, 1985-1999 and undated, 2 folders (Box M5)
      - Pintasilgo, Maria de Lourdes, Portugal, 1986-2000 and undated (Box M5)
      - Pitanguy, Jacqueline, Brazil, 1997-2001 (Box M5)